Guide to the Paul Kagan Utopian Communities Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Paul Kagan utopian communities collection
1845-1986
1910-1975
WA MSS S-1737
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
29.54
(58 boxes) + 9 broadsides, 2 art, 4 cold storage
The collection contains both primary and secondary source material accumulated by Kagan while conducting research for his book, New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community. In addition to personal correspondence pertaining to his research, and drafts of his manuscript for the book and related writings, Kagan's collection contains letters, photographs, documents, notes, writings, and other visual material and printed material, which document 19th and 20th century utopian communities, most of which were located in California. The archives of Walter Millsap, William and Lucille Riker and John and Agnes Varian, participants in Llano del Rio and Newllano, Holy City, and Halcyon respectively, are also present. The photographic component of the archive is particularly strong: numerous original photographs taken by community members are supplemented by field photographs that Kagan took in the 1970s, as part of his research. Utopian communities represented in the collection include Llano del Rio, Newllano, Holy City, Halcyon, Fountaingrove, Icaria Speranza, Kaweah, Krotona and Ojai Valley, Pisgah Grande, Point Loma, and the Tassajara Zen Mountain Center.
Kagan, Paul, 1943-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The William Reese Company obtained the papers from Paul Kagan's widow and the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library purchased them on the Frederick W. & Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana in 1993. The 2009 acquisition was purchased from the William Reese Company in 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 48-56: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
During the course of his research, Kagan acquired copy prints and negatives from other institutions. Where possible, the institution holding the original images has been identified and contacted, and permission has been obtained to retain the copy prints and negatives in this collection, with the understanding that they are for reference use only, and are not to be reproduced. Kagan also acquired photocopies of the historian Robert Hine's notes. They are for reference use only and are not to be reproduced.
Associated Materials
Walter Millsap / Keikichi Akana Imamura Family Papers (WA MSS S-1590)
BIOGRAPHICAL AND HISTORICAL NOTES
Paul Kagan, photographer and author of the book New World Utopias, was born in 1943. After receiving a degree in history from the University of California at Berkeley in 1965, he worked as a television news writer, photographer, graphic artist, and magazine art director. Kagan spent five years researching New World Utopias: A Photographic History of the Search for Community (New York: Penguin Books, 1975). Initially, the National Institute of Mental Health provided funds for Kagan to photograph the remains of California 'utopias'; a few years into the project the California Historical Society gave him funds to research and collect the records and contemporary photographs of those communities. During this time Kagan organized the Utopian Studies Center at the California Historical Society Library (San Francisco). At the time of the book's publication, Kagan described himself as writer/researcher and still photographer for the Television Health Information Project at University of California Medical Center, San Francisco. Paul Kagan died in New York in 1993.
New World Utopias focuses on the history of ten utopian communities in California, dating from 1870 to the present. The philosophical underpinnings of these colonies ranged from the religious (Fountaingrove, Holy City, Pisgah Grande, the Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, and the Theosophical communities of Halcyon, Point Loma, Krotona and Ojai) to the secular and socialist (Icaria Speranza, Kaweah, and Llano del Rio). Kagan also gathered information about six additional, contemporary utopian communities (The Farm, International Re-Education Foundation, Lama Foundation, the Rosicrucian Non-Sectarian Fellowship, Self-Realization Fellowship, and Vedanta Society of Southern California), which he planned to treat as another chapter in his book. That chapter, however, was never written.
Fountaingrove, the earliest of the the religious communities Kagan studied, was established in 1875 by Thomas Lake Harris, founder of the Brotherhood of the New Life and of three colonies in New York between 1861 and 1867. Fountaingrove, described by its founder as a Theo-Socialist community, was situated in Northern California, two miles north of Santa Rosa. Harris was the "primate," or "pivotal man" chosen by God. His spiritualist doctrine included teachings such as Divine Respiration, which enabled the brotherhood to commune with God. Through the efforts of a Japanese-American, Kanaye Nagasawa, Fountaingrove developed a successful winery. In 1891, Harris' complex theories of spiritual counterparts and celibacy resulted in a widely publicized accusation of sexual license and immorality. Harris left Fountaingrove the next year, and the community quickly deteriorated. In 1900 he sold the property to five members of the colony. Kanaye Nagasawa became sole owner in the 1920s, and operated the winery until his death in 1934.
Holy City was another utopian community built upon the religious views of a dynamic central figure, William Riker, who founded the Perfect Christian Divine Way in San Francisco in the second decade of the 20th century. Known as "Father Riker," or "The Comforter," he received communiqués from God through his nerves that carried undertones of white supremacy. He established Holy City ("the world's most perfect government") in 1918, in the Santa Cruz Mountains, south of San Francisco. Holy City was situated near a state highway on the way to Santa Cruz, a popular beachside resort, and featured a grocery store, garage, and gas station, which enabled Riker and his followers to take commercial advantage of the vacationer traffic. Riker, a colorful figure, was frequently in court: over the years he was charged with reckless driving, fraud, sedition, breach of promise, and murder. He ran for Governor of California four times, unsuccessfully. Gradually, the inhabitants of Holy City drifted away, and by the mid-1960s the colony was abandoned. Riker died in San Jose in 1969.
Pisgah Grande, located in Southern California, in the Santa Susanna Mountains, was established in 1914 by Dr. Finis E. Yoakum, after he made a dramatic recovery from a life-threatening injury at a prayer healing clinic. Thereafter, Yoakum dedicated his life to God and became well known in Los Angeles for his work with the underprivileged and his belief in the power of prayer. At Pisgah Grande, Yoakum and his followers formed a self-supporting community, distinguished by a hilltop prayer tower, where they maintained a permanent vigil. This short-lived community apparently never outgrew its dependence upon Yoakum's presence; when he died in 1920, Pisgah Grande struggled on for only a year before disbanding.
The Tassajara Zen Mountain Center, founded in 1967, is a traditional Zen monastery in the Santa Lucia Mountains south of Monterey. It was established by the California Zen Center, led by the Center's founder, Shunryu Suzuki. The Center is open during the summer for classes; the rest of the year it serves as a place where a core group of followers meditate, work in the fields, and gather for lectures, following Zen tradition.
The Theosophist Communes of Point Loma, Halcyon, Krotona and Ojai arose from the Theosophical Society formed in 1875 by Helena Petrovna Blavatsky and Henry Steel Olcott. The Society based its creed on spiritualism and the occult. In 1878 Blavatsky and Olcott enlarged the scope of their Society by establishing the International Headquarters of the Theosophical Society, first at Bombay and then at Adyar, a suburb of Madras. When Blavatsky died in 1891, a schism developed between the Theosophists in India, represented by Olcott and Annie Besant, and the Theosophists in America, led by William Q. Judge and later Katherine Tingley. The two sections were never reunited, but by the time of Olcott's death in 1907 more than 600 branches had been formed in 42 countries.
In 1897 Katherine Tingley founded the Universal Brotherhood and Theosophical Society at Point Loma, a peninsula in San Diego. Tingley's beliefs mixed humanitarianism with the occult. Members received no wages, and worked at tasks assigned to them on a rotating basis. At its peak, Point Loma had approximately 500 members. The community, a school run according to Theosophist principles, introduced the first Greek theater in California. Katherine Tingley died in 1929; her successor, Gottfried de Purucker, struggled to save Point Loma from financial problems which beset the colony until its demise in 1941.
In 1898, Dr. William H. Dower and Mrs. Francia LaDue of the Theosophical lodge in Syracuse, New York received mystical instructions to shun Tingley's teachings in favor of the original teachings of Blavatsky. In 1903 they moved to a valley near Pismo Beach, north of Santa Barbara, named it Halcyon, and instituted the Temple of the People. There they built a sanatorium, and a cooperative society named the Temple Home Association. The community experienced internal troubles throughout its existence, and in 1912 the cooperative society disbanded. One of the community members, John Varian, whose papers are in the collection, was an Irish poet and musician; he and his wife Agnes lived in Palo Alto and later at Halcyon.
Albert Powell Warrington, an Adyar Theosophist, established a Hollywood, California outpost in 1912, named Krotona. It had few communitarian principles; instead the group shared a common Theosophist philosophy. When Hollywood became too crowded in 1924, Krotona sold their 15 acres of land and moved to the Ojai Valley, northeast of Los Angeles. Here they established a school of Theosophy.
Icaria Speranza, located fifty miles north of San Francisco Bay, was established in 1881 by two French men, Armand Dehay and Jules Leroux. Dehay and Leroux had emigrated from an Icarian community in Iowa, Jeune Icarie, which had been founded on the principles set forth in Etienne Cabet's Voyage en Icarie, published in 1840. At Icaria Speranza each member was given monthly labor premiums based on the number of days they had worked in the colony's vineyard and orchard. The rest of the Iowan Icarians joined them in 1883; however, they encountered unanticipated legal difficulties in selling their Iowa land, which made it difficult for the California colony to get out of debt. As a result, by 1887, Icaria Speranza had been declared dissolved.
The Kaweah Colony was settled in 1885 by the Co-Operative Land Purchase and Colonization Association of California, led by Burnette G. Haskell and James J. Martin, labor activists from San Francisco. When they and the members of their Association filed claims for land in the Sierras of eastern Tulare County, the government became suspicious of the large number of claims and closed the land to entry while it investigated. During this four year investigation, the members of the Association settled near the Kaweah river and made plans to establish a cooperative timber company. The colony was governed by the principles of Marxian socialism, using the concept of the labor-check, a system of currency based on units of work performed. In 1890, however, the Kaweah colonists lost all claims to their land when Congress established the Sequoia National Park, and the community soon disbanded.
Llano del Rio, situated in the Mojave Desert near the San Gabriel Mountains, was established in 1914 by Job Harriman, a socialist from Los Angeles who ran unsuccessfully for governor of California in 1898, for vice-president under Eugene Debs in 1899, and for mayor of Los Angeles in 1910. The socialist colony attracted 900 members within three years and established a successful agricultural program, stores, libraries, and kindergartens. In 1917, insufficient water supplies prompted Harriman to relocate the colony to west-central Louisiana, near Leesville. This new colony was named "Newllano"; here in 1920, George Pickett succeeded Harriman as manager. The remnant of the California colony, which had been left under absentee management, was forced into involuntary bankruptcy, placing Newllano under a financial burden. These problems were compounded by the Depression, and in 1935, after a long rebellion against the administration of George Pickett led by Eugene D. Carl, the colony was placed in receivership. Walter Millsap (full name: Leander Walter Millsap, Jr.) was an active Llano "alumnus," as well as an inventor, socialist, and founder of United Cooperative Industries in Los Angeles, who gathered material for a history of the Llano colonies. His papers are included in Kagan's collection.
In addition to these many extinct communities, Kagan studied a number of modern utopian communities, which were still active at the time of his work. The International Re-Educational Foundation is one of many organizations established by the Reverend Sun Myung Moon, leader of the worldwide Unification movement. The Foundation set up the International Ideal City in Mendocino County, California, and the International Pioneer Academy in San Francisco. The Rosicrucian Fellowship Non-Sectarian Church was founded in 1911 by Max Heindel at Mt. Ecclesia in Oceanside, California. The group follows a spiritual philosophy based on the occult and pantheism.
The final two groups that Kagan studied originated in India. The Self-Realization Fellowship, headquartered in Los Angeles and founded by Paramahansa Yogananda, is an international religious society based on the teachings of Yoga and a direct experience with God achieved through meditation. The Fellowship operates the Ananda Meditation Retreat, the Ananda Spiritual Community, the Ananda School, and the Ananda Farm, all in Northern California. The Vedanta Society of Southern California, which operates under the spiritual guidance of the Ramakrishna Order of India, is a religious order founded in 1897 by Swami Vivekananda and other disciples of Sri Ramakrishna, who taught that all religions are different paths leading to the same goal. The Vedanta Society of Southern California was established in 1934, and maintains a temple, convent and monastery at Hollywood, a temple and convent at Santa Barbara, and the Ramakrishna Monastery at Trabuco Canyon near Santa Ana.
Paul Kagan also researched two modern utopian communities outside of California. The Farm was founded as a collective by Stephen Gaskin in 1971 in Summertown, Tennessee. At its height there were 1500 members. The second community, the Lama Foundation, was established twenty-five miles north of Taos, as a study center for the awakening of consciousness. The Foundation runs a farm, a K-12 school in Taos, and a summer school.
Scope and Contents
The Paul Kagan Utopian Communities Collection contains both primary and secondary source material accumulated by Kagan while conducting research for his book, New World Utopias. In addition to personal correspondence pertaining to his research, and drafts of his manuscript for the book and related writings, Kagan's collection contains letters, photographs, documents, notes, writings, and other visual and printed material, which document several 19th and 20th century American utopian communities, most of which were located in California. The photographic component of the archive is particularly strong: numerous original photographs taken by community members are supplemented by field photographs that Kagan took in the 1970s, as part of his research.
The Kagan collection, housed in 56 boxes and comprising 29.25 linear feet, consists of five series: Series I, Walter Millsap Papers; Series II, William and Lucille Riker Papers; Series III, John and Agnes Varian Papers; Series IV, Paul Kagan Research Files; and Series V, Paul Kagan Writings. Boxes 38-47 contain Oversize material; boxes 48-55 contain Restricted Fragile Papers; box 56 contains Restricted Fragile Art Objects.
The size and internal cohesiveness of the first three series, which contain papers obtained from founders or members of four of the utopian communities (Llano del Rio and Newllano, Holy City, and Halcyon) sets them apart from the other source materials in the collection. Accordingly, Series I, II, and III are defined by provenance, while Series IV contains original and duplicates of source materials on these same and many other utopian movements, obtained from a number of other individuals, as well as from the research collections of other libraries and historical agencies. Finally, Kagan's own research correspondence and manuscripts are gathered together as Series V.
The organization of materials in Series I-IV is defined first by topic (name of utopian settlement) and then by format of material (correspondence, documents, photographs, other visual material, printed material, etc.). Series V is organized into materials relating to New World Utopias, and Other Writings. In a few instances, personal papers unrelated to the utopian experience but which accompanied the utopia-related papers from former members are included as well. A number of serial runs, as well as pamphlets and other Western printed ephemera, have been removed for separate cataloging; their provenance has been traced in catalog records. In addition, a number of newspapers in unreadable condition were discarded after it was verified that copies were available in other libraries. Appendix A lists those serials and other printed items removed for separate cataloging, as well as the serial titles and newspaper issues that were discarded.
Series I, Walter Millsap Papers (1892-1970), (boxes 1-13) contains correspondence, documents, writings, printed material, photographs, and other visual material, organized into three subseries: Llano del Rio and Newllano, Cooperative Work after Llano, and (Millsap's) Personal Papers.
The Llano del Rio and Newllano subseries includes material created during the years the colonies were active, as well as material produced after Newllano disbanded. The correspondence files contain originals of letters received and carbons of letters sent, all arranged in one chronological file. Most of the letters were sent or received by Walter Millsap, but letters of other colonists are present as well, including Newllano leader George Pickett, and prominent colonists Chester Peecher, Sid Young, and A. H. Moore. All but the first folder of correspondence was written after the disbanding of Newllano, and there is a distinct set of letters from former Llano colonists, written in 1944-1945 in response to a call by A. H. Moore for reminiscences about the colonies (box 1, folders 3-4). There are also letters from others relating to the foreclosure at Newllano, and the subsequent attempt to recover the property.
Reports and Communiqués, which belonged to Mellie Miller Calvert, an early Llano colonist, contains letters and newsletters written to all members of the Llano community after Newllano disbanded. Many of the reports and communiqués were written by Walter Millsap; in them he passed along news of the recovery of assets at Newllano, and drafts of his history of Llano, as well as announcements of upcoming stockholder meetings and minutes of meetings. Related materials are located in the extensive Writings section. These include essays by Walter Millsap in addition to various writings by Llano colonists. Millsap's works include a large number of drafts for Gateway to Freedom (box 1, folders 29-31, box 2, folders 33-37), a history of the Llano and Newllano colonies, which was published in part in Upton Sinclair's Epic News. (Excerpts of the Gateway to Freedom appear in newsletters found in the Reports and Communiqués.) Many of the manuscripts in the Writings by Others were written in response to A. H. Moore's request for reminiscences of Llano colony. Authors here include A. H. Moore himself, R. V. Shoemaker, Robert K. Williams, and Ernest S. Wooster.
Two sections, Documents, and Photographs and Postcards, contain only contemporary colony materials, including the minutes of the Llano del Rio General Assembly, Special Assemblies, and Board of Commission meetings from 1915-1917, as well as documents relating to the Newllano receivership case. Photographs and Postcards, which is arranged into Llano del Rio and Newllano groupings, contains a variety of photographic formats: simple snapshots, studio photographs, glass plate negatives (for which contact prints have been made), nitrate negatives (for which contact prints have been made), photographic postcards, and photograph albums. The work of Meyer Elkins, photographer at Llano Studio in California, is gathered together (box 2, folders 79-80). The glass plate negatives include a large number of personal images belonging to Llano colonist Alice Constance Austin, an architect and city planner, and probably were gathered by Walter Millsap. (Architectural records and drawings for buildings designed by Austin are filed with Printed Material and Other Visual Material, respectively.) In addition, there are six photograph albums present. Three of them contain some duplicative images of Llano del Rio, which suggests that the albums were intended to serve as yearbooks or some other sort of memorial.
Printed Material contains Austin's architectural records (mentioned earlier), plus miscellaneous newspapers, clippings, broadsides and pamphlets about Llano del Rio and Newllano. Following Printed Material are the Walter Millsap Research Files, which consist of materials he generated in the course of his work on a history of Llano and Newllano.
The second subseries, Cooperative Work after Llano, reflects Millsap's involvement with the United Cooperative Industries in Los Angeles, the Epic News newspaper, and Ucopia newsletter. The material is organized into Correspondence, Documents, Writings by Walter Millsap, Writings by Others, and Printed Material. The Correspondence consists principally of original letters to Walter Millsap and carbons of letters from him. There are three letters from Upton Sinclair in 1933 and 1934 in response to letters from Millsap (carbons of which are present) about articles in the paper Sinclair edited (box 6, folders 133-134). Some of the other letters present were written to Millsap as editor of Epic News. In addition to the Correspondence, the Documents and Printed Material contain information on Millsap's work with United Cooperative Industries. There are receipts and inventories for U.C.I., as well as the "Ucopia" newsletter that was sent out to U.C.I. members.